A Guide to the Robert Selph Henry Papers, 1861-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Robert Selph Henry Papers, 1861-1971
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1989-020
4.3 cu. ft. 4 boxes
Spanning 1861 to 1971, The Robert Selph Henry Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, photographs, and clippings concerning Henry's research on the Civil War, focusing on the Confederacy and Nathan Bedford Forrest, and also railroad history. This collection also contains Henry's Southern Historical Association (SHA) and Association of American Railroads papers.
Henry, Robert Selph
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by Virginia Tech Special Collections in 1989.
Biographical Note
Robert Selph Henry (1889-1970) was born in Clifton, Tennessee on October 20, 1889. He graduated from Vanderbilt University with an L.L.B. in 1910 and a BA in 1911. He served as a Captain of Field Artillery in WWI, and remained in the Army Reserve, rising to the rank of colonel, until his retirement in 1952. He worked for the newspaper in Nashville (1907-1913), served as secretary to the Governor of Tennessee (1913-1915), practiced as a lawyer in Nashville (1915-1921), and worked for the railroads, first as Director of Public Relations for the Nashville, Chattanooga and St. Louis Railway (1921-1928), then as Assistant to the Vice President of the Nashville, Chattanooga and St. Louis Railrway (1928-1934), and lastly as as the Vice President of the Association of American Railroads (1934-1958).
Henry was also a historian of the Civil War and the railroads. He published several books including The Story of the Confederacy (1931), The Story of Reconstruction (1938), First with the Most Forrest (1944), and This Fascinating Railroad Business (1942). Henry also served as President of the Southern Historical Association (SHA; 1957).
Scope and Content Note
The Robert Selph Henry Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, photographs, and clippings concerning Henry's research on the Civil War, focusing on the Confederacy and Nathan Bedford Forrest, and also railroad history. Most subject files involve research notes and photocopies or transcriptions of primary sources such as diaries, letters, and reminiscences. This collection also contains Henry's Southern Historical Association (SHA) and Association of American Railroads papers.
The collection dates from 1861 to 1971; however, most of the Civil War letters and diaries contained in this collection appear to be either later reprints, transcriptions, or copies of the original. The dates given in this finding aid correspond to the year for the original document. Many of the photographs are reproductions as well.
Arrangement
This collection is organized thematically in alphabetical order by folder title.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following book has been removed from the collection and has been catalogued for the rare book collection: Diary of Capt. Heber S. Thompson, Seventh Pennsylvania Volunteer Cavalry, May to December, 1864
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civil War; Railroad
Contents List
- Advertisements - Forrest Quote, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Assn. of American Railroads, 1934-1953 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Bell, Brig. Gen. Tyree H. Bell, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Biography - R. S. Henry, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Mary Forest Bradley, (Correspondence), 1943 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Burlington Zephyrs, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
- Chapin, Edward Young, 1944-1954 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Chattanooga, TN - 1869, (Recollections of Mr. Caldwell), n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- "Chattanooga and the War," 1959 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Civil War Articles - Various Authors, 1932-1957 (Box-folder 1-10)
- Civil War Articles - No Author, 1931, n.d. (Box-folder 1-11)
- Civil War Letter, Camp Near Richmond, 1862 (Box-folder 1-12)
- Civil War Letters - Merrick, 1862 (Box-folder 1-13)
- Civil War Letter - Gen. Ruggles, ca. 1864 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Civil War Letter - Post, 1888 (Box-folder 1-15)
- Cockrell, Monroe, 1947-1958 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Confederate Research Club, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 1-17)
- Confederate Songs, 1950 (Box-folder 1-18)
- "Diary of Capt. Herber S. Thompson" 7th PA Volunteer Cavalry, 1864 (Box-folder 1-19)
- "Diary of J. Pugh Cannon," Transcript, 1863-1864 (Box-folder 1-20)
- Diary - Chaplain Charles Todd Quintard, Transcript, 1864 (Box-folder 1-21)
- Ewell (Lt. Gen. R.S.) Letter to R. E. Lee - Transcribed, 1865 (Box-folder 1-22)
- Forrest, Nathan Bedford, 1935-1955 (Box-folder 1-23)
- Forrest, N. B. - "Bankruptcy on Debtor's Petition," Copy of 1869 Document, 1944 (Box-folder 1-24)
- Forrest, N. B. - Notes (6 folders), n.d. (Box-folder 1-25 to 1-30)
- Freight Tariff for 1870, 1870-1937 (Box-folder 1-31)
- Grady, Henry Woodfin, "The New South," 1886 (Box-folder 1-32)
- Hood's Campaign, Middle Tenn., Transcript of Conversation, 1868 (Box-folder 1-33)
- Hughes, Robert Morton, 1933-1936 (Box-folder 1-34)
- Illustrations - Civil War, Copies, n.d. (Box-folder 1-35)
- Inka, Miss. (Battle of), (Notes), n.d. (Box-folder 1-36)
- Jackson, "Stonewall" - Hall of Fame Bust, 1957 (Box-folder 1-37)
- Ku Klux Klan, 1930-1944 (Box-folder 1-38)
- Kuhler, Otto, 1935-1952 (Box-folder 1-39)
- Letters, n.d. (Box-folder 1-40)
- Letters, 1930 (Box-folder 1-41)
- Letters, 1931 (Box-folder 1-42)
- Letters, 1932 (Box-folder 1-43)
- Letters, 1933 (Box-folder 1-44)
- Letters, 1934 (Box-folder 1-45)
- Letters, 1935 (Box-folder 1-46)
- Letters, 1936 (Box-folder 1-47)
- Letters, 1937 (Box-folder 1-48)
- Letters, 1938 (Box-folder 1-49)
- Letters, 1939 (Box-folder 1-50)
- Letters, 1940 (Box-folder 1-51)
- Letters, 1941 (Box-folder 1-52)
- Letters, 1942 (Box-folder 1-53)
- Letters, 1943 (Box-folder 1-54)
- Letters, 1944 (Box-folder 1-55)
- Letters, 1945 (Box-folder 1-56)
- Letters, 1946 (Box-folder 2-1)
- Letters, 1947 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Letters, 1948 (Box-folder 2-3)
- Letters, 1949 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Letters, 1950 (Box-folder 2-5)
- Letters, 1951 (Box-folder 2-6)
- Letters, 1952 (Box-folder 2-7)
- Letters, 1953 (Box-folder 2-8)
- Letters, 1954 (Box-folder 2-9)
- Letters, 1955 (Box-folder 2-10)
- Letters, 1956 (Box-folder 2-11)
- Letters, 1957 (Box-folder 2-12)
- Letters, 1958 (Box-folder 2-13)
- Letters, 1959 (Box-folder 2-14)
- Letters, 1960 (Box-folder 2-15)
- Letters, 1961 (Box-folder 2-16)
- Letters, 1962 (Box-folder 2-17)
- Letters, 1964 (Box-folder 2-18)
- Letters, 1968 (Box-folder 2-19)
- Letters, 1969 (Box-folder 2-20)
- Letters, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 2-21)
- Lincoln, Pres. A., 1954 (Box-folder 2-22)
- Mrs. Joseph Luxton (Mother of N. B. Forrest), 1925-1943 (Box-folder 2-23)
- Mexican War, 1950-1959, n.d. (Box-folder 2-24)
- Newspaper Articles - Civil War, 1925-1956 (Box-folder 2-25)
- Newspaper Articles on Forrest, 1942-1956 (Box-folder 2-26)
- Pemberton, John C., 1931-1938 (Box-folder 2-27)
- Photographs - Civil War, 1920, 1951, n.d. (Box-folder 2-28)
- Photographs - Railroad, 1863-1938 (Box-folder 2-29)
- "Portraits of the Iron Horse," 1936-1945 (Box-folder 2-30)
- Postcards, 1945-1956 (Box-folder 2-31)
- Printed Material (4 folders), 1903-1961 (Box-folder 2-32 to 2-35)
- Pullmans, 1940, n.d. (Box-folder 2-36)
- Railroad Notes and Papers 1, n.d. (Box-folder 2-37)
- Railroad Notes and Papers 2, ca. 1920s - 1940s (Box-folder 2-38)
- Railroad Notes and Papers 3, 1939-1948 (Box-folder 2-39)
- Railroad Notes and Papers 4, 1938-1941 (Box-folder 2-40)
- Reviews - R. S. Henry Books, 1931-1960 (Box-folder 3-1)
- Sansom, Emma, 1954 (Box-folder 3-2)
- Shelton, R. - 14th TN (typed) Letters, 1862-1864 (Box-folder 3-3)
- Slave Insurance Policy from 1855, 1931 (Box-folder 3-4)
- Southern Historical Assn., 1881, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 3-5)
- "The Story of the Confederacy," 1930, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
- "The Story of Reconstruction" (2 folders), ca. 1930s (Box-folder 3-7 to 3-8)
- Story of Reconstruction Notes - 1865, n.d. (Box-folder 3-9)
- Story of Reconstruction Notes - 1866, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)
- Story of Reconstruction Notes - 1867-1868, n.d. (Box-folder 3-11)
- Story of Reconstruction Notes - 1869-1870, n.d. (Box-folder 3-12)
- Story of Reconstruction Notes - 1871-1873, n.d. (Box-folder 3-13)
- Story of Reconstruction Notes - 1874-1877, n.d. (Box-folder 3-14)
- Streight-Forrest Route, 1948 (Box-folder 3-15)
- Sturgis's Route From Ripley to Brice Cross Roads, n.d. (Box-folder 3-16)
- Swift, Eben - Letters, 1888 (Box-folder 3-17)
- Telegrams, 1934-1950 (Box-folder 3-18)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1940 (Box-folder 3-19)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1941 (Box-folder 3-20)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1942 (Box-folder 3-21)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1943 (Box-folder 3-22)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1944 (Box-folder 3-23)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1945 (Box-folder 3-24)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1946 (Box-folder 3-25)
- "The Fascinating Railroad Business," 1947 (Box-folder 3-26)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3-27)
- "This Fascinating Railroad Business," 1950s (Box-folder 3-28)
- Tom Thumb, n.d. (Box-folder 3-29)
- "Trains" - 1930s, 1933-1938 (Box-folder 3-30)
- "Trains" - 1940s, 1943-1949 (Box-folder 3-31)
- "Trains" - 1950s, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 3-32)
- Ware, Dr. John N. - Correspondence, 1943-1956 (Box-folder 3-33)
- Wiley, Bell I. - Letters, 1942-1957 (Box-folder 3-34)
- Wyeth, Dr. John A. to General E. W. Rucker, 1896 (Box-folder 3-35)
- Yancey, William L., 1861 (Box-folder 3-36)
- Civil War Copies of Images and Letters for Publications, n.d. (Box 4)